<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The aunswere of the Lords the Estates Generall of the Vnited Prouinces of the Lowe-Countries, to the letter of the Archduke of Austria, heere-after inserted together vvith the proposition done in the name of the sayde arch-duke to the forenamed states, by Otto Hartius, and Jeronimus Coomans, learned in the lawes : also, the extract of certaine letters, written out of the campe before Groning.</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18451.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S458</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22444099</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22444099</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25543</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08085)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25543)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1754:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The aunswere of the Lords the Estates Generall of the Vnited Prouinces of the Lowe-Countries, to the letter of the Archduke of Austria, heere-after inserted together vvith the proposition done in the name of the sayde arch-duke to the forenamed states, by Otto Hartius, and Jeronimus Coomans, learned in the lawes : also, the extract of certaine letters, written out of the campe before Groning.</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1594]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Printed first at Middelburgh, by Richard Schilders, Printer to the Estates of the Land and Earledome of Zealand, 1594."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Austria.</term>
               <term>Austria --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25543:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25543:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Aunſwere</hi> Of the Lords the Eſtates generall of the vnited Prouinces of the <hi>Lowe-Countries,</hi> to the Letter of the Archduke of Auſtria, heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after inſerted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together</hi> VVith the propoſition done in the name of the ſayde Arch-duke to the forenamed States, by <hi>Otto Hartius,</hi> and <hi>Jeronimus Coomans,</hi> learned in the Lawes.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Alſo, the extract of certaine Letters, written out of the Campe before <hi>Groning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>❀ Printed firſt at Middelburgh, by Richard Schilders, Printer to the Eſtates of the Land and Earledome of <hi>Zealand. 1594.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Wolfe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="response">
            <pb facs="tcp:25543:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25543:2"/>
            <head>The Aunſwer of the generall Eſtates of the vnited Prouinces of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> to the Letter of the Archduke of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE generall Eſtates of the vnited <hi>Low Countries,</hi> in the aſſembly of their people, haue opened and redd the Letter of the moſt excellent Prince <hi>Erneſtus,</hi> Archduke of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundie. &amp;c.</hi> cloſed and ſealed with the Seale of his Highnes, dated in <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> the ſixe day of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Month of May: receiued the twelfth of the ſame Moneth, by the hands of Maiſter <hi>Otto Hartius,</hi> and <hi>Ieronimus Coomans,</hi> learned in the Lawes: at whoſe inſinuation, doone the next day after, to ſay the xiij. day: haue the <hi>16.</hi> day of the ſaid Moneth, in the aſſembly of their aforeſaid people, deliuered vp in wryting, as appeareth by the clauſes in the aforeſaid Letter inſerted. And after due examination of the afore-ſaide writing and Letter, (to the end they might open to his Highnes their good intent &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,) haue declared, and by theſe preſents doo declare, that ſince the time that their people (for vrgent occaſions and very neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,) were conſtrained to put themſelues in Armor, for the behoofe of the freedome of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> with the priuiledges and iuriſdiction of the ſame in generall, and of the Prouinces, people, Citties, and Indwellers of the ſame in particuler: and for repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Spaniſh tyrannie, and lordly gouernment, ouer the conſciences, bodies and goods, of the Inhabitants of the ſayde <hi>Low Countries,</hi> their wiues and children: their meaning and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent alwaies was, &amp; yet is, to maintaine the ſame (with the helpe of GOD) againſt the Spanyards and their adherents.</p>
            <p>With thys ſtedfaſt hope, that almightie God through his gracious goodneſſe and bleſſing, ſhall further the ſame their vpright meaning and good intent, which the longer, the more is not onely found to be for their owne <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> but alſo toucheth the eſtate of all their neighbours, Kings, Princes, and Common-wealths. Like as their people haue found alſo (through the power of Gods mighty hand,) that hee hath not onely bleſſed their meanes and pretences, but alſo hath mooued the harts of Kings and Princes their Neighbours, to the vpholding &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25543:3"/>of their aforeſaid needeful and vpright intents. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of their people do attribute the praiſe only to God, truſting in the vnalterable power of his godly Maieſtie, expecting at his hands and goodnes a laudable iſſue and ende of heauie warres: hauing ſure confidence that their people of the <hi>Low Countries</hi> in general, ſhall be vnited, and brought into their olde eſtate and proſperitie. The which they more earneſtly doe deſire, in that they haue well proued and tryed, and beſides that, do yet very well remember the commodities, quietnes, and pleaſantnes of peace, reſt, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: but alſo contrariwiſe, haue found and felt the incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, diſquietnes, and vnfruitfulnes of warres. But like as his Highnes declareth in the ſaid letter, and profeſſeth his good will and affection, and thanketh al thoſe, that are vprightly affectioned to the vnity and proſperity of the <hi>Lowe Countries:</hi> ſo haue they and their people alſo great cauſe to complaine before God and all the worlde, ouer them, which yet vnder the pretence of peace, doo ſeeke and practiſe the ſpilling of innocent blood of Chriſtians, and to further the ruine and vtter decay of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the Spaniſh counſel (who now in all reſpects do finde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſore offended with theſe Countries) will worke more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely then before: vſing thereto ſuch horrible ſhamefull, and vnlawfull proceedings, as heeretofore hath not beene heard or thought on.</p>
            <p>And much more is the vtter ruine and decay of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries to be looked for, in this reſpect that it is well knowne to all the world, into what extremity they are come, and how their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes do ſtand. Namely the deſtruction of innocent blood by the Hangmans hand, of many thouſand innocent and guiltleſſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, aſwell men as weomen of all qualities, amongſt which haue beene ſome of the principalleſt Lords of the land. The violation of the principalleſt freedomes, priuiledges, and iuriſdictions of the <hi>Lowe Countries,</hi> and Citties, aſwell in generall as perticuler, many murthers, burnings, violation, erations, concuſſions, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her enormities and execrable deedes, after very many remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, ſupplications, with ſending of certaine of the Neither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh Lords into Spaine, as namely amongſt others the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of <hi>Bergen,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Monteng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> who there were ill dealt withall, and vſed againſt the law of Nations.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:25543:3"/>
            <p>Alſo the interceſſion of great Potentates, done in vaine, to the end that the <hi>Lowe Countries,</hi> the people, Citties and good Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants themſelues, might be ſuffered to inioy their laudable free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes priuiledges and iuriſdictions: and the tyranny of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh nation and their adhearents ouer their conſciences, bodies and goods, might be caſt of, which hath brought their people to theſe aforeſaid extreamities. And therefore it may pleaſe his Highnes to vnderſtand that the States before named, haue with good inſight and pondering, proceeded, as they doo nowe ſhewe themſelues, towards the welfare of theſe Countries and inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof, like as in times paſt, and in like caſes is alreadie paſſed.</p>
            <p>And that their people canont beleeue, much leſſe be aſſured any waies, of any alteration of the Spaniſh humors, which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore haue beene more apparant, and part of them promiſed, with great loſſe and damage to theſe Countries. For in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of theſe warres, the out-rage of the Spaniardes was ſo great, that all were put to death, which came into their power.</p>
            <p>And to vſe ſuch like law, for ſo laudable a matter, as the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their natiue Countrey, againſt forraine tyranny, either with their counſel or deedes, that not only their plaine Countries were waſted: but alſo many principall Citties with murthering, robbing burning, and other horrible, execrable and vnnaturall dealing, euen whilſt ſuch matters were intreated of, and let the people of theſe Countries be aſſured, that no other thing is to bee looked for at the Spaniards hands, which in the end wil not turne to the vtter ſhame, ruine, and ouer-throwe of theſe Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</p>
            <p>There began the blood thirſty Counſell to chaunge, and theyr humors, to alter in apparance: but in ſuch ſort that the people marked that it would fall out hard with them to come with anie force: and therefore haue had many parleys and conferences. And the firſt entreatement of peace began in <hi>Anno. 1574.</hi> which the Eſtates of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> (vſing their olde honeſt and ſimple manner) were mooued to ſeeke redreſſe of their griefes, by writings remonſtrations and others. The fruit and effect of this intreaty, was perfectly perceiued and ſeene in <hi>Brabant,</hi> by the firſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25543:4"/>ouer-fall of the Citty of <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> named by the Spaniards in their Hiſtories, <hi>Fuere Villacos:</hi> and in <hi>Hollande</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> with their ſtrong and ſeconde beſieging of the Citty of <hi>Leiden,</hi> which notwithſtanding through the grace of God, the truſtines of her Confederates, and their owne goodnes: were preſerued from the power of the enemie. Yea, with ſuch an extraordinarie terror to the Spanyards which lay before the Citty, were by the mightie hand of God ſo daunted in their courages, that they ran confuſedly out of <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſhortly after did meane to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe the goodly Cittie of <hi>Vtricht,</hi> as they and others of the Spaniſh nation, had done the ſame yeere, in the former Citty of <hi>Antwerpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This firſt deceitfull entrety of peace, comming to this effect and ended, the ſecond was taken in hande, at the interceſſion of the moſt high and mighty Emperour <hi>Maximilian,</hi> his Highnes Father, in <hi>Anno, 1575.</hi> within the Citty of <hi>Breda.</hi> Howe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the ſame entreatie was meant on the Spaniardes ſide, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the welfare and proſperity of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> the cléere teſtimonies doo bring with them: and the fruites thereof was no other thing, but more preparation of warres then before. So that ſhortly after, there followed the ouer-fall of the Citties of <hi>Bueren, Leerdam, Oudewater, Schoonhouen, Bommeney,</hi> and the beſieging of the Citty of <hi>Sirikzea:</hi> whereby hath procéeded, what the Spaniards and their adherents, haue done, with theyr robbing, murthering, and other horrible deedes. Yea, the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of Citties, on their partes, haue beene in ſuch haynous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that no man could longer ſuffer or abide the ſame, but haue proclaimed them enimies of the <hi>Low Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherevpon followed the vnion and confederacy at <hi>Gaunt,</hi> in Nouember, <hi>Anno. 1576.</hi> betwixt the Netherlandiſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, and for the conſeruation of the welfare of the ſame, theyr freedoms and Lawes: is well knowne to euery one, howe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly the ſame vnion and confederacie was accepted on the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſide, and what deceit and enmitie was mingled amongſt it. The Letters of <hi>Eſtoued,</hi> the violation vſed by <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe declaration, from the Spaniſh Counſell, brought ouer by the Baron of <hi>Selles,</hi> and publiſhed in <hi>Mecklin,</hi> the ſeuerall dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings at <hi>Louen,</hi> the ſending of ſundry Embaſſadors of diuers Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25543:4"/>haue giuen ſufficient teſtimony thereof, in <hi>Anno 1577.</hi> and <hi>1588.</hi> How deceitful, ſhameful, hurtful and greeuous, the iſſue of the entreaty of peace was, begun at <hi>Cullen</hi> with ſuch great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, is well knowne to euerie one. Alſo that during the ſame, not onely the Prouinces of <hi>Haynault</hi> and <hi>Arthois,</hi> with ſundrie other principall Citties, were ſeduced to this particuler tractati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but alſo all outward force vſed towards the Citty of <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricht.</hi> And many priuie and naughty practiſes put in vſe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prouinces, and amongſt the people of the ſame, to moue the ſame to tollerations, to their vtter ruine and vndooing.</p>
            <p>With what practiſe afterwards, were the Citties of Flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders brought to tractation, and what braue prohemes were there done, and what excellent end it had, is manifeſted by the actes thereof. To what intent was the intreaty of peace in <hi>Anno 1587.</hi> and <hi>1588.</hi> What deceit and force lay hid vnderneath the ſame: the Spaniſh <hi>Armada</hi> (come ouer during the ſame intreaty and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome by Gods mighty hand) hath made manifeſt. To what intent afterwards in <hi>Anno 1591.</hi> was the Emperors Maieſtie occaſioned anew, to take the affaires of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> into his hands, the Leaguers doe teſtifie, which from time to time, are ſent out of the <hi>Lowe-Countries</hi> againſt the French King. Whereby it is made more manifeſt, that the Spaniards will and meaning is, with their adherents, to be alwaies in wars and Armor, vſing the pretext of furthering of Romiſh religion. But to ſpeake the trueth, for their pretended generall domination &amp; ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, which they would eſtabliſh ouer all Chriſtendome: and to rob and ſpoile all Kings, Princes, Landes &amp; Common-wealths, of their due rights and prerogatiues. Like as of late was prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed againſt the Quéene of England, by ſending ouer that proude and mighty <hi>Armada,</hi> in <hi>Anno 1588.</hi> And the tryumph before the victory, openly ſung and put forth in print, is manifeſted. And likewiſe the wars and buſines in Fraunce ſince the ſame yeere, namely in the beginning of the next yeere after, about the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Crowne of Fraunce, not onely the King now preſent, and all the Princes of the bloode, but generally all French-men, are ſo entreated of the Spaniards (vnder the name of <hi>Infante,</hi>) becauſe of the Spaniſh Counſell and ſuffrence, by the Duke of <hi>Ferris,</hi> and other Spaniſh Miniſters, neither is there any tryall,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25543:5"/>but by the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> and others reuolted from the League, by arreſt of other iuſtifications put foorth in print, is made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>And as good regard is to be taken, to the complot made in Scotland, in <hi>Anno 1592.</hi> with many of the principall Lordes there. That twentie thouſand Spaniſh ſouldiers ſhold haue been ſent and receiued into Scotland, which in the yeare paſt, is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull come to light (for which ſome were puniſhed with death.) And it is not to be beleeued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame was builded vpon any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foundation, or otherwiſe dealt withall, then practiſed with the Biſhoppricks of <hi>Collen</hi> and <hi>Strasburg,</hi> the Dukedomes of <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, Cleue</hi> and <hi>Berg,</hi> and the imperiall Citty of <hi>Aichen,</hi> which not onely diuerſe &amp; ſundry intercepted letters, but alſo the deedes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues do manifeſtlie declare. Finally, what agreement was there pretended with the greateſt Princes of <hi>Italie?</hi> howe were they buſied in ſeeking to bring <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> vnder them? (wherewith all the vnited Prouinces were alſo meant.) To the ende that therein they might make their <hi>Sedem belli,</hi> faſt and ſure againſt all Chriſtendome. Yea, in ſuch ſort, that men would rather the Turke ſhould be let in, and a great part of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: then theſe warres, &amp; men of warres, prepared &amp; deſtenied to the deſtruction of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and the people thereof.</p>
            <p>And to ſumne vp the matter, how the Emperours Maieſtie and the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> haue been dealt withall (only to the furthering of the ſaid ſpaniſh gouernment,) appeareth euidentlie by the letters ſigned by the the King of Spaine, whereof a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation is heereby inſerted (the originall ſet apart) which letters do mention alſo, the points propounded by his Highnes: to wit, that the meaning of the Spaniſh cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell is not (through his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) for any good meaning of Chriſtendome: much leſſe to bring the <hi>Lowe Countries,</hi> to reſt and quietnes. In that it appeareth, that the Earle of <hi>Fuentes, Don William</hi> of <hi>Saint Clement,</hi> and <hi>Stephen di Narro,</hi> (al three ſpaniards) are appointed for his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Counſellers for matters touching the <hi>Lowe Countries,</hi> that the ſame ſtrangers ſhould rule his Highnes, howe the Lordes of Neitherland are to be truſted, the <hi>Low Countries</hi> to be ruled, and the vnited Prouinces to be brought vnder ſubiection. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates do not doubt, but his Highnes hath well vnderſtood, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25543:5"/>through the practiſe and procurement of the aforeſaid Earle of <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes,</hi> and <hi>Stephen di Narra,</hi> not long agoe Doctor <hi>Lopez,</hi> Phiſition to the Queenes Maieſtie of England, was promiſed fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand Crounes to poyſon her Maieſtie. And that the ſame Doctor <hi>Lopez, Emanuell Lewes Tinaco,</hi> and <hi>Stephen Ferrera de Saua</hi> (all companions of the aforeſaid murtheriſh feate) were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in England &amp; iudged to death. That through the practiſe and procurement of the ſaid <hi>Fuentes</hi> and <hi>di Narra: Emanuell Andraga</hi> tooke on him to poyſon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French King with a Noſegay of flowers or Roſes, ſo tempred with pouder, that the very ſmel therof ſhould poiſen him to death. We omit the matter (and what thereby will fal out) of <hi>Michael Remichon,</hi> (otherwiſe naming himſelfe <hi>Triuiere</hi>) a Prieſt of <hi>Namour,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſent two monthes agoe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Bruſſels</hi> diſguiſed in the apparel of a ſouldier, into the vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces. Who hath confeſſed, that he and certaine other murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, with fayre promiſes and money, were ſent foorth to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the moſt excellent Prince, <hi>Morrice</hi> borne Prince of <hi>Orrenge,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Naſſow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, that his Princely Highnes yongeſt Sonne, (beeing onely tenne yeares olde,) and lying in the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> at Schoole bee not taken from thence, as his eldeſt Brother the Earle of <hi>Buren,</hi> againſt all right, freedome and priuiledges of the Countrey, and all lawes of Nations, was violentlie carried out of <hi>Louen,</hi> looking dailie to be murthered. Like as the ſaid Spaniſh counſel through their murtheriſh acts, did kil the Prince of <hi>Orrenge</hi> his Highnes father. Out of which his Highnes, and euery one without any gainſaying, may well vnderſtand, by what people, and by what meanes, the good Inhabitants of the <hi>Low Countries</hi> haue beene deceiued, and howe little the Eſtates haue forgotten the ſame. Being occaſioned to ſay as much nowe of this aforeſaid entreaty of peace of the Spaniards, and to iudge with like affection thereof, as of theſe matters rehearſed. Yea, now ſuch horrible and ſhamefull matters do come to light againſt the Realmes of Fraunce, England, and theſe Countries: as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the like was before. So that the humors of the Spaniſh counſell are altered, for any goodnes towards theſe Countries, neither is there any appearance that the ſame ſhould be furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſeeing that they are now moſt highly offended.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:25543:6"/>
            <p>Or that theſe Countries (whereunto they pretend ſuch right) ſhould be better dealt withall, then the Kingdoms of Fraunce, England, and Scotland, whoſe ſubiects are in like authority and like dignitie. For which cauſes, the foreſaide Eſtates, in reſpect of their dutie and oath, are bound and forced, to take better heede and regard, to the crafty practiſes of the aforeſaid Counſell. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the vnited Prouinces, for ſuch horrible pretended murther of the King of Fraunce, and Queene of England, with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parence of warres ſince his Highnes comming into the <hi>Lowe-Countries,</hi> begun and continued againſt the Crowne and eſtate of Fraunce.</p>
            <p>And yet are not againſt it, but that all former pretexts ceaſing, do take the motion ſo neere their harts, as the good allience, friendſhip and Communalty of the matter requireth. And all is, that a man might well beleeue, that his Highnes hath a miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſuch murthering and diuiliſh actes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet notwithſtanding greater heede is to be taken, to the purpoſe of the ill will, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and intent of the King of Spaine, and Spaniſh counſell, of whome his Highnes hath his Commiſſion and authoritie (who alſo at all times may reuoke the ſame, and put another in his place) againſt which no man can aſſure him, with any condition. Whereby the aforeſaid generall Eſtates, cannot perceiue that they ſhould reape any fruite or profit by the aforeſaid intreatie of peace, either within the ſaid vnited Prouinces, or without the ſame, with the Queenes Maieſtie of England, (with whom in ſuch matters and others they ſtand faſt in confedracy,) nor yet with the French King, and other Potentates, Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealths of theſe Countries the whole Chriſtian cauſe, their friends and alliances. But do meane to haue their refuge vnto almightie God, at whoſe mightie hand and goodnes, they looke for a laudable iſſue of their righteous cauſe, (as they haue alwaies pondered, and yet do conſider, howe alterable worldly matters are) expecting not onely the welfare of the vnited Prouinces: but alſo of the Neitherlandiſh Prouinces to the furthering of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and holy word.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Thus ended and reſolued in the aſſembly of the Lordes E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates generall, in <hi>Earles Hagh.</hi> 
                  <date>the <hi>27.</hi> of May. <hi>Anno. 1594.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:25543:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Ernestus,</hi> by the grace of God Archduke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> &amp;c. Knight of the Order, Lieutenant, Gouernour, and Generall Captaine.</head>
            <p>HOnourable, Noble, Worſhipfull &amp;c. The inward natural loue and affection, which we beare to the reſt, and welfare of the <hi>Lowe Countries,</hi> and the miſliking which we haue long had of diſcord and miſerie wherein they are: is the principall cauſe that hath mooued vs to take vpon vs the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, with ſtedfaſt hope that almightie God would giue vs his grace, that we might releaſe you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe heauy and ciuill warres, which now haue laſted ſo long, to the great griefe, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and hinderance of the ſaid Countries, and of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. For if men will conſider in what eſtate and proſperitie they were in times paſt, when they were in peace and vnitie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der due obedience of the houſe of <hi>Burgundy</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the good rules and orders kept the ſame time, in points of iuſtice, pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy and other orders of wars, whereby the aforeſaid Countryes were increaſed and renowned throughout all Kingdomes and Countries.</p>
            <p>Alſo the great riches which was ſo aboundant there, by meanes of the dealings, aliences, confederacies, nauigation and Traffick, which they had to <hi>Portingall, Spaine</hi> and <hi>India:</hi> we are ſure that there is no man of vnderſtanding, that is not ſorry with his whole hart, for ſo great and pittifull alteration of the ſaid Countries, in the time of ſixe and twentie yeares or vpwadrs, with the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold oppreſſions, exactions and greeuances, which the poore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people in that time, haue ſuffered, and in ſundry places ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, yet preſently is ſuffered. And that do alſo wiſh, that with the firſt, ſome good end and tollerable meanes might be wrought, to bring the ſaid Countries, into their former eſtates common tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, due obedience and agreement. Wherevnto alſo wee do imploy all our thoughts, and with the ſame pretence and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning are come hether, leauing the company of the Emperours Maieſtie our Soueraigne Lorde and Brother, and others our Bretheren and Kinſfolkes, our natiue Countrie, and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of ſo many Kingdomes and Countries, committed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25543:7"/>vnto vs, with departing from other things, not néedful heere to be repeated: to the end we might find you ready to come to our good meaning and intent. And although we doubt not, but that all the ſame is well knowne to your people, as well by common report as otherwiſe, and by them accepted, as wee hartily deſire the ſafety, reſt and welfare of you, and thoſe which come after you: yet notwithſtanding, wee haue thought it neceſſary and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, to let your people knowe &amp; vnderſtand the ſame by theſe preſents: as well to abandon all ſuſpition, as to the more neerer reuealing of our foreſaid goodnes and vpright inclination to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you, and thoſe which might looke for the ſame at our hands. Foraſmuch then, as the matter toucheh you ſo neer: you, your people, and thoſe which are vnder you, ſhould ſet before your eyes, the luck, fortune and welfare, which thereby might come and redound to your natiue Countrey, ſo pittifully oppreſſed and ſpoyled through theſe long laſting warres. And ſo far foorth as the good luck which you had this laſt yeare (as matters of warre bee ſickle and inconſtant) ſhould make any to forget the foreſaid euils and miſchiefes, and not to think vpon thoſe which might chaunce and fall out, and thereby ſeeme to aſſure themſelues ten fold, without any accepting of this good occaſion: ſhall it not then bee needefull to thinke on examples and things paſſed, which teacheth that in ſhort time ſuch great alteration may happen: that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that is ſoone loſt, which ſhortly before hath beene gotten with greate labour, honour and reputation. Wherefore we do pray you both hartely and earneſtly, that you will altogether take good counſell therein, deepely weighing and pondring all things, and you your ſelues offer vs ſuch laudable and honeſt conditions of peace, that by meanes thereof it may be perceiued, the ſooner the better, that you be not ſuch, as ſeeke to lengthen or prolong the warres, which bringeth ſo many kindes of oppreſſions to the Communally, as is well knowne to all men: but that thereby the ſame might be brought to ſome perfect ende, ſure reſt and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes.</p>
            <p>And for our parts, we wil ſhew you with our déedes, that no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit or craft is hid therein, not ſeeking any thing els, then a true ſtedfaſt peace: which, and all that we do, is with good earneſt, and ſimplicity, to the furthering of the Common wealth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25543:7"/>if you ſhew your good will: Then ſhall you ſhewe what you eſteeme and thinke of vs, and deſire to be in time of neede, as is beſt knowne to you your ſelues. Like as the bringers hereof Maiſter <hi>Otto Hartius</hi> and <hi>Ieronimus Coomans</hi> learned in the lawes, ſhall declare, being thereto appointed by vs, with proffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our good will towards you. Praying almightie God. &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Bruſſels</hi> 
                  <date>the fift of May, <hi>Anno. 1594.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Vnderneath ſtood, Yours to commaund <hi>Erneſtus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The ſuperſcription was,</p>
               <p>¶ <hi>To the Honorable, the Eſtates of <hi>Gelderland, Holand, Zealand; Freeſland, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricht, Ouer-Jſell,</hi> and others, aſſembled at <hi>Earles Hagh</hi> in <hi>Holand.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="proposition">
            <head>¶ The propoſition done by <hi>Otto Hartius,</hi> and <hi>Jeronimus Coomans,</hi> learned in the Lawes: to the Lords the generall Eſtates of the vnited Nether-landiſh Prouinces.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS wée lately had gotten Paſport of the Lordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Eſtates, that wee might come into theſe vnited Prouinces, for the diſpatching of our buſines and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler matter, (for which we yeeld the ſaid Lordes freendlie thanks, and thoſe which put to their helping hands for furthering of the ſame,) with offering the like to be done, &amp; to be ſorrowed for on our ſide, for thoſe which ſhall néede to goe from hence: and the ſame beeing brought to the knowledge of his Highnes, the Arch-duke of <hi>Auſtria Erneſtus,</hi> he hath thought good to ſend vs, that we ſhoulde in his name ſalute you, proffering you all good: and to declare vnto you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the principall cauſe which moued him to ſend vs into theſe Countries, was the ſinguler loue &amp; affection which he hath alwaies borne to the welfare and quietnes of the ſame. And that he hopeth, that God of his grace will ſende ſuch meanes, that through him, the ſame may be vnited againe in good peace and tranquility, as it was before the beginning of theſe ciuill troubles: towards the which, and to vnderſtande hys good will and meaning the better, hee hath charged and commaunded vs, to recite vnto your Worſhips, the Letters which we deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the twelfth day of this Month of May. Hoping y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25543:8"/>ſhall thereby cleerely perceaue his will and meaning is, to ſettle a ſure peace and long during vnitie in theſe Countries, and that the indwellers thereof may be pacified, to their content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And although the ſame in the yeare paſt, prooued to bee in vaine, and alſo when any entreaty of peace, or accord is agreed vpon, ſtraightwayes through miſconſtruing therof: they fall into new enmity and warres, (through whoſe occaſion and dooing, is not at this time to be ript vp, and God graunt it be not hereafter neither.) So that if your Worſhips ſhould be conceiued with any miſtruſt of ſuſpicion, or mooued with any miſliking, to deny ſuch reaſonable conference, eſpecially, becauſe that lately matters haue fallen out, according to the will and pleaſure of your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes yet doth his Highnes hope, that the ſame ſhall not reſt or depend vpon any temporall and alterable proſperitie, whereby this preſent occaſion ſhould ceaſe, or come to none effect. For which all honeſt people, and louers of the whole Lands, peace and vnitie: ſhould deſire and wiſh your worſhips to ſet the ſame before your eyes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that all worldly matters, haue their howres, times and ſeaſons. And like as there is a time of diffidence: thereafter may well come and followe a ſeaſon of confidence. That all men toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought to truſt vnto, and to looke to the ſecurity of himſelfe and his ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there neuer roſe vp in any Country, ſo great wars tumults or diſcorde, either publiquely or perticularly, but it was laſtly ended and layde downe, more with entreaties and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then with force of Armes. For warre is of ſuch vnhappie fruitfulnes, that it bringeth out, a beard to one, and a foote to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that it neuer went well or proſpered with any Prince, eſtate or Common wealth, which refuſed or denyed a laudable proffer of entreaty of peace. Touching which, wee had rather haue the examples of our time, and remembrance thereof, to paſſe vntouched: then by repeating or reauealing therof, to remember the faults of them or others. For if your Worſhips at this time ſhould bee mooued or detracted, with any kinde of diffidence or miſtruſt, or thinking to refer the ſame till another time: yet, wee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25543:8"/>hope you will reſpect the time and ſeaſon, and howe the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is put to the arbitriment of your Worſhips and of other perſons, to ſay, with his Highnes ſprong out of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> whoſe vpright dealing, vnderſtanding, vertue and honour, well beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſuch a Prince. Whereby only may be vnderſtood, that ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or eight one after another of the ſame houſe haue come to bée Emperours, not by ſucceſſion, which is giuen aſwell to euill as good Princes: but by the voyces and free election of the Electors, and Common-eſtates of the Empire, commonly grounded on princely vertue and conſtancy, in worde and deede, of him that is elected.</p>
            <p>Like as not long agoe, appeared in the perſon of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the ſecond, Father to his Highnes, who for his moderation and goodnes, might haue been accounted for a ſpeciall ſelected inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Common wealth, for reforming of diſcords and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies of religion, to hold vp in ballance, and to lay downe: Such as the like of him hath not beene in times paſt: or likelie to follow.</p>
            <p>And following the footeſteps of the ſame, hath by vs ſent the original letter to your Worſhips, which wee doubt not is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by your Worſhips with ſuch frendly and good affection, as we do hold aſſuredly the ſame to be written without enemity.</p>
            <p>We pray therfore and earneſtly requeſt you: that your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes, will duely ponder the contents of the ſame, with ſuch an anſwere, that his Highnes and all honeſt people, may the ſooner the better, haue cauſe to conceaue ſome good hope of their long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired peace, which they looke to haue through your worſhips wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and prouidence. With humble petition, that if your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips repre-ſenting this honourable aſſembly, or any one in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler, ſhould finde himſelfe agreeued, with any difficulty, in any wordes, points or vnderſtanding of the aforeſaid writing of hys Highnes: we are ready at all times to explane the ſame if wee may ſtand you in any ſteede.</p>
            <p>Alſo we hope that our interpreting thereof, ſhall bee to your Worſhips contentment. Which in effect is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayned in the force of the clauſes of the ſaid letter of Credent, and ſtandeth vpon our perſons. Friendly praying you to accept thereof in good part.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:25543:9"/>
            <p>And note withall by the way, (with your Worſhips leaue,) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at by the confeſſion and declaration of certaine perſons which are taken and examined: his Highnes is empreached, that hee ſhould haue pretended the death of Earle <hi>Morrice</hi> of <hi>Naſſow,</hi> through the meanes of the ſame perſons, or otherwiſe, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhould haue been done to the Earle of <hi>Barlaymont.</hi> Being an abſurd and impudent delation, becauſe they neuer came, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer paſſed from his Highnes, in the leaſt reſpect, or from his houſe or ſtock, from which in times paſt, neither ſuch infamous deedes haue proceeded, nor with Gods helpe ſhall proceede.</p>
            <p>We are heere in the name of his Highnes, to enquire the truth of the matter, praying your Worſhippes that the priſoners may be ſafely kept, and ſent with ſome Comiſſary to <hi>Antwerp</hi> or <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> with writing to his Highnes that they at certaine time and place, be ſent back againe, or els to be tranſported to <hi>Breda,</hi> being vnder the iuriſdiction of this gouernment, to the ſaid Earle of <hi>Barlaymont,</hi> who for this purpoſe ſhall be accompained with a Comiſſary in the name of his Highnes, and appeare there in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to examine them vpon ſuch circumſtances and perticulers, as ſhalbe aduiſed, and found needefull to be examined of. With due paſport to be giuen. Or els if it pleaſe your Worſhips to aduiſe ſome other expedient meanes, that the trueth may be diſcouered, which ſurelie ſhould redound to the vnburthening and excuſing of his Highnes: and your Worſhips ſhall thereby attaine great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for your good iuſtice, as in ſuch caſe the like hath not beene thought of, or of any other perticuler conſideration, which the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners ſhould ſay and declare, or els not publiſhing the ſame, to the preiudice of any man, or contemning any good meaning of his Highnes. &amp;c. Propounded and done in the aſſembly of the Lords the generall Eſtates, the ſixteenth of May. <hi>Anno 1594.</hi> in <hi>Earles Hagh.</hi> And ſubſcribed by vs <hi>Otto Hartius,</hi> and <hi>Ieronimus Coomans.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25543:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
